New York City, 1971.
Subtitled by CLARITY
♪ Everywhere is freaks and hairies ♪
♪ Dykes and fairies,
tell me where is sanity ♪
♪ I'd love to change the world ♪
♪ But I don't know what to do ♪
♪ So I'll leave it up to you ♪
♪ Population keeps on breeding ♪
♪ Nation bleeding,
still more feeding economy ♪
♪ Life is funny ♪
♪ Skies are sunny ♪
♪ Bees make honey ♪
♪ Who needs money, Monopoly ♪
I'm done.
♪ I'd love to change the world ♪
♪ But I don't know what to do ♪
♪ So I'll leave it up to you ♪
♪ Oh yeah! ♪
LIFE
I'll have the prints
from the Ali/Frazier fight by six.
Make it four. Everybody out.
Serial killers, footloose, lies, Jesus.
That's what sells magazines, Bob.
You should lose all those
corny war photos out there.
What have you got for me? I don't have
time for a cocktail hour sip'n grin.
I want you to speak
at the opening of my exhibition.
I just want you to say
something about how great I was.
Wa-- Was?
Yeah, how great I was, I mean...
How great I still am of course.
But, you know, way back then
when you could be great,
when the truth still meant something.
So, yeah. You just have to say that...
I'm the greatest photographer
that Life Magazine has ever have.
But you aren't.
You're the single most impossible
photographer the Life has ever had.
Well, fuck it! Just say it that then.
I can't Gene.
I told you when you called.
I'm out of town that week,
I got a board meeting.
Look, Bob, I'm done.
I'm tired, my body is older than I am.
I am always in goddamn pain.
I can't trust my fucking dick anymore.
Constantly a foul mood.
Even the fucking drugs bore me,
my kids won't speak to me.
You know, I could go head first
into a fucking shrimp cocktail
at any given moment.
And I'm broke.
I'm sorry, Gene.
I wasn't looking for your sympathy,
I was just stating the facts.
By the way, if anyone
should be asking for sympathy, Bob...
It should be you.
Look at this drake you're turning out.
Amazing!
No laddering.
You got all the way up
in your high horse, just like that.
We practically
give this magazine away to our readers.
We cover all the major issues
that touch their lives,
issues from all over the country,
all around the world.
We do it every week.
On top of that, we fight
television sets for the same eyeballs
you took for granted
would always be there.
It gets worse all the time.
What we do, what I do every day
is find a way to pay for all of this
and keep it going.
What we put on the cover,
what we put in the middle of those stories
that's what does that!
Wow! Well...
Your horse is obviously
much higher than mine.
Consider this as an overdue "thank you".
A royalty cheque you found
on an old pair of corduroys.
Cash it at the branch on 17th and 6th.
Keep it off the books that way.
You know that you're only sitting
behind that desk because of dogs like me.
Right?
Good luck, Gene.
Don't waste what time you got left.
You're a dick, Bob.
Date is Sunday, February 28th, 1971.
Well, it's me, I've done it.
I'm done with retrospecting.
And now I don't have
to do any more things.
Yeah.
I sold all of my stuff, you know,
my equipment what have you.
And I'm gonna make sure
that you guys get the money for that...
I know, I hate to sound modern but...
I think it's time for me to...
Goddamnit!
I'm coming!
- Mr. Smith...
- Now is not the time.
Hi, I'm Aileen, and this is
our photographer, Geichi.
Thanks. Thank you.
Why is this man giving me cookies?
Fujifilm, we are here
for the advertisement.
Oh! That, yeah, right, Christ!
Well, look, I'm gonna
have to level with you.
I have consumed
quite a whole lot of alcohol...
What did he say?
Geichi says you're his
favorite photographer
and the reason
he's got into the field.
Oh, that's very nice. That's very nice.
And what about you?
Have you never heard of me?
Not before this morning, no.
So you're not a fan?
It's too early to say.
Alright.
What do you want me to do?
They want you to say that Fuji color film
is more vibrant than any other
color film on the markets.
It's the only color film you trust.
Turn that shit off, turn everything off.
Do they really want me to say that?
Yes, it was part of the deal.
Oh fuck!
You know, I've never shot in color, ever.
Not once, never, ever.
And anyone who knows my work
will know that.
So that's a very big problem.
I'm sorry but it's in the contract.
Did I sign the contract?
Will Naughton is playing
at Francesco's tonight.
Join me.
Alright.
Let's get on
with the puppet show.
So, are you going to give me
a photography lesson?
Oh listen, I would, but I damn
near sold all of my equipment.
I need to send money to my kids,
rents, way overdue and...
My bank account
just walked under the duck.
- So...
- What duck?
Not a real duck, never mind.
Sometimes you just get fed up with...
You know, sometimes...
I used to be more fun.
I used to be a lot more fun,
I swear to you.
I bet you were a fun dad
to have five kids.
No, no, I wasn't.
Not even close.
I was never there,
I was gone all the time.
Absent. No leagues...
No barbies, no easy bake ovens.
I missed it all.
I had a great time
with you tonight, Aileen.
I...
I didn't just happen
to get this job with you.
Uh huh.
There's a company in Japan.
That's been dumping their toxic waste
into the sea for years.
The Chisso Corporation.
People are getting sick and die.
The people need help.
There is a resistance on the ground.
But we need global attention.
We need you
at the shareholder's meeting next week.
Well, I'm afraid that Japan
has seen the last of me, kid.
That was 25 years ago.
Listen...
If that's why you're here
I'll put you on the long list of people
that I've disappointed.
I'm terribly sorry,
but I've got a few things to do.
Defenestration and whatnot, you know.
Sorry, I did that all wrong
and I've upset you.
It wasn't my intention..
No, no, it was a lovely night.
It was?
Yeah.
Here's some information.
Please have a look.
My number is on the envelope.
Take care, Aileen.
LIFE
I love the suggestion for the center,
it looks really... It looks ideal to me.
- The center is very strong.
- Yeah.
- Robert?
- Good--
Robert, a huge crisis in Japan.
Mercury poisoning.
Here's your Pulitzer Prize.
- Gene, what the hell?
- People are dying, Robert.
Yeah, all day, every day.
It doesn't mean
you get to fuck up my layout.
Oh goddamnit!
Am I interrupting your little layout?
No, you guys just go on and make
a room for your fucking Oil of Olay ads
while innocent people
drop like flies, huh Bob?
You talking about Minamata?
Yeah! See? She knows. She's smart.
Is there anybody else here
who's as smart as her?
A factory there has been contaminating
the bay of some fishing village.
At first they called it "the strange
disease", then "dancing cat fever."
And now it's simply called
the Minamata disease.
It's fucking monstrous.
I've been following it
in the Herald and the Times,
small stories, every couple of months.
But no one has really covered it.
I mean it's in the goddamn fish,
and that's all those poor people
have to eat.
The Times has a Tokyo desk.
And we have deadlines
literally in one hour.
So that sounds to me, Bob,
like a... yeah,
time is of the essence.
And you know that the cover up
is gonna be as much of a story
as the story itself.
I gotta go, come on.
You expect me to send you?
- You'd be a real dumbass not to.
- Gene, stop.
A moment, if you please.
This is the story, Bob.
- You know this is the story.
- I'm not sending you.
What? Why not?
Gene, I'm gonna throw you
out of the goddamn window.
I wish you would have done that
the last time I was here.
Gene, listen closely.
If I don't send you...
you can't fuck me on this,
you understand what I'm saying?
- No.
- Call me at home.
Don't call me here.
And you can't disappear on me again.
Bob...
I would never disappoint you, again.
Just try not to disappoint yourself.
Kumamoto, Japan
Gene, let's go.
I'm coming.
Hello.
Take off your shoes.
- Excuse me.
- Thank you.
Listen! Children are asleep.
So, let's be quiet.
You must be quiet,
the children are sleeping.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
This is not much.
- Please, have some food.
- Thank you very much.
Honestly I don't really have
so much of an appetite right now.
But it's definitely coming back,
this food is...
I'd like, I'm interested...
What is... I'm interested in this.
Try this one.
Is it good?
It is good, isn't it?
- It is good.
It is good.
Well...
Actually...
It is hard to talk about those things.
It is not just about us.
It's not easy to speak
about certain things.
Akiko is our eldest.
Akiko is our oldest.
They have tried to tell us...
that what she has is cerebral palsy,
but we knew better.
They tried to tell us it was
cerebral palsy but we knew better.
She was born ill and she still is.
She was very sick and she remained sick.
She will never get better.
And she will never get better.
But then...
But our family bonds are strong.
We are a strong family.
Akiko is... our treasure.
She is our treasure.
We have six children,
and we all work hard
to take care of Akiko.
It takes five hours a day to feed her,
but she brings us closer as a family.
When you meet her, you'll see.
She is a beautiful soul.
We don't want to bring attention
to our family...
but we don't have a choice.
I drive a truck for Chisso.
For Chisso!
But it's not enough to take care
of a family with the needs we have.
I will translate you later.
Can you...
Can you please thank
them for their kindness?
Their generosity
and for their hospitality?
And if it's at all possible...
to photograph Akiko, perhaps tomorrow.
- We thank you for your kindness.
- Not at all.
If you don't mind...
Can we take some photos
of Akiko tomorrow?
Well really, that kind of thing...
...you'll have to excuse us
I'm sorry. No.
I'm sorry.
- I will make your beds.
- Thank you.
- She will make our bed.
- Okay.
- Please! There's nothing much left but...
- Thank you.
Aileen?
Would you mind to ask
if he might have just a little...
- You know... snoop.
- Yeah.
Excuse me! Excuse me!
He seems that he cannot fall asleep.
Do you have anything to drink?
A drink?
Just one minute.
Does he have something?
- He loves whiskey for sure.
- Probably.
- Whisky.
- Good.
- Good night.
Many are tired of fighting,
or they don't want to
bring attention to themselves.
Then there's us,
the direct Negotiations Group.
We are not so easy to keep quiet.
I can imagine.
Kiyoshi is one of the lead activist
for the direct Negotiations Group.
Yeah, I got a light. I got a light.
His son was born with the disease.
Kiyoshi also has it,
but it's yet to be officially recognized.
- Thank you.
- Sure.
It's in my hands and in my vision.
But it's my son, and those
like him, that keep me going.
- Keep me fighting, you know?
- Sure.
Does that ever affect
your ability to shoot?
I may waste a little more film
than I should.
But for some reason with the camera
I'm not so bad.
What is...
What's your endgame in this?
Chisso doesn't believe us, patients.
They don't believe we're suffering.
So we want to look
the President in the eyes.
We want him to see us
and then tell us that we don't suffer.
And what makes you think
he's gonna listen to you?
I don't know.
Maybe if we make a noise loud enough.
They won't have a choice.
With you, we have a better chance.
Chisso Manufacturing Plant
Last night I rode my bicycle
all the way up to Tsunagi...
...because I heard about one family.
At first, they didn't want to let me in.
I asked them why...
they haven't been seen
in the neighbourhood lately.
I could see the shame on their faces.
It turns out their young boy
was very sick with Minamata disease.
I asked them to join us,
that we wanted help.
They considered but ultimately
their shame won out and they declined.
They love their son just as they should.
In all cases of Minamata,
there is someone to blame.
The suffering is caused by an evil...
...that we know as a fact!
So, here we are.
We have a choice.
We can let the world know.
If we are loud enough, they will listen.
Accept your responsibility!
Come on!
Is he alone?
I think so.
I hate that shit.
I used to fucking hate gym class.
They used to make us
all sit down in a row.
Cross-legged, you know?
And I couldn't do it.
My legs just don't work like that.
They don't work like that.
And the...
I know you don't understand
a word that I'm saying.
But that's not gonna stop me
from talking. So...
You might as well just dig in, kid.
Do you like jazz?
Well, you better cause jazz...
jazz is what we have got.
It's just fucking jazz.
Improvisation, everything.
See this?
Anyone can do this,
anyone, takes nothing.
You point, focus, click.
And most importantly, fuck up.
Fuck up, because,
that's the only way to learn.
So...
You take it, kid, I'm sick of it.
I should have known better...
coming here.
So you go on, play the music.
I'm...
I'm not really sure
if I can hear it anymore.
I don't believe you.
I mean, what kind of photographer
gives his camera away?
Unbelievable.
Passing the torch, Aileen,
is how one dies gracefully.
- Somebody said that once.
- You alright?
What? Yeah, Kiyoshi.
It's probably best you know this now,
I disappoint people.
And I disappoint people always.
Where are we?
Aileen found you two
a little home to stay in.
What? Really?
- Yes.
- Me and her?
Yes.
Wow! That was nice.
Come with me.
We also put together
a dark room for you.
I set it up just the way
you have back home.
Thank you.
Pleasure.
Gene, good news,
we're moving up your piece.
I think we might have an issue
with more photographs than car ads
for the first time for three years.
It turns out there's a UN
environmental conference
in Stockholm in a month,
very first of its kind.
We need to coordinate two.
Gee-wiz Bob!
I don't think I've heard you this excited
since they faked the moon landing.
Millie is shaking every tree
with an anti-nuke folks
and the WHO here and in Japan.
We have all the science
to highlight your images.
- Is he saving his receipts?
- So, how is it going out there?
It's fun, it's fun.
I'm having a great time.
I wish you were here
I'd let you buy me a drink.
There's no wiggle room
on this one, Gene.
If we don't have
the images by next week
we won't make it.
You know what? What?
- Gene...
- I got a bad connection, Bob.
- I've got a bad connection.
- Gene...
I think that I might have had
a little something, drink...
And I didn't even know
what I was doing.
I asked the people to give
whatever cameras and film they had.
Thank you very much.
Maybe you can join me
thanking the people.
Oh yeah. Thank you. Thanks.
Bow!
Alright.
Thank you.
That's my camera.
- Is this yours?
Yeah, that's me, that's mine.
Great. Got it. Alright.
That's right.
How do we turn it to photos?
- What?
- How is it turning to photos?
Then you turn it like this,
then turn it like this.
Come here, you do it.
Give me your hands.
Take that, okay?
Put that hand there.
Okay, now, I got you.
Just turn it like that, alright?
- Like that.
- Aren't you afraid of
touching me?
You are not afraid to touch me?
Why would I be?
Your hands shake
because you have Minamata disease too?
No, no, no.
I just drink a bunch.
What this kid's name?
Shigeru.
Gene.
It's getting late,
maybe he should be in bed, no?
Thanks kid.
He wants to learn how to make
the film tape into big pictures.
I'm not really here...
to give photography classes.
Especially kids.
OK. I'll teach him.
I'll teach you.
You take it.
Here, you got it?
And you go take some pictures.
And we'll develop them later.
Okay?
Thank you.
Arigato.
Okay, pal.
Pretty good that kid.
- You like that one, huh?
- Can I have it?
No, you can't just have it, no.
Maybe I can help?
You know...
The Native Americans, they believed
that a photograph would take a piece
of the subject's soul.
But what gets left
out of the fine print is...
that it can also take a piece
of the photographer's soul.
You understand
what I'm saying? It...
It will break your heart.
So if you take it...
You take it seriously.
Agreed?
Chisso Factory Hospital
- This way.
- Put your stuff here.
Put your stuff here.
It's for my aunt.
Goddamn!
I'm glad that worked.
- May I?
- Yes.
OK, I'm gonna see
if I can find something
we can use
at the shareholders' meeting.
It's okay to take a picture.
Just don't show his face.
Alright, listen, people must see
what's going on behind the eyes
because that's where the truth is.
It's in empathy.
- The thing... I need faces.
- We need empathy here.
Okay.
Thank you sir.
Thank you very much.
OK, let's go find the nursery.
Let's... let's turn around
and go this way.
Just keep going.
Just slip in here, quick, quick!
Gene, Aileen, I found the lab.
Dr. Yamashita has been
the chief doctor for Chisso
since the first victim showed up.
They had to be running tests.
They must have found something.
Hey, I found something.
It says that the cat he fed
from Chisso pipe water
reacted just like their patients.
Spasms.
Paralysis.
Convulsions.
Which is exactly what happens
when one is poisoned with mercury.
It literally destroys brain tissue.
And for 15 years they knew.
They knew, Gene.
And they kept poisoning people.
Give me that.
You turn around, pick up your camera,
check your settings.
You cannot let your emotions
run the show
'cause you will fucking lose,
and sometimes you might fucking die.
Focus on the photograph you want to take.
Focus on what you want to say.
Do it now.
Remember how it affected
your emotions, right?
How did it make you feel?
Was it unpleasant? A menace?
There's an evil...
So, you are changing...
many things, yeah, okay?
Now...
Take it out.
Throw it in the liquid.
So, here's a little secret of mine.
Use your hands a lot.
Caress the image.
Warm the print with your...
body, from your hands.
That's how you tell your story.
Yeah.
Here. It's for your hands.
Thank you.
What for?
Oh wait!
Don't move, don't move, don't move.
Click.
Aren't you supposed
to ask permission first?
Permission is like asking for a kiss.
No, it destroys the moment,
you just gotta take...
Like that?
Something like that, yes, yeah.
Just...
Try not to forget
about the fine print, kid.
If human beings are still
the masters of creation...
we have to overthrow this poisoned world.
Is this civilisation?
Is this the so-called
period of rapid growth?
But done at the cost
of sacrificing countless lives?
Our beautiful blue ocean is now made
into a deadly sea by those people.
So, if you are a human being,
please stand up...
and fight!
Remember, we never wanted a war.
But we have to fight.
Let's make this the last battle
for humanity.
Please stand up!
Go! Go!
- What are you doing?
- No. No.
Gene!
It's okay.
I'll be back.
Mr. Smith, come in.
- Thank you.
- Please sit.
Would you like something to drink? Water?
You know, I actually think
I'd rather wait
until I get outside the building
before I drop dead.
So... perhaps a soda pop, you know...
With the top still on it.
In the bottle.
OK.
Thank you.
Mr. Smith, do you know
what "parts per million" means?
Without getting confused
by all the science,
it is a very, very small amount.
And small amounts are accepted.
Even in this bottle.
Unopened bottle of Cola.
There may be the tiniest amount
of some material
you might not expect or appreciate.
But it's microscopic, barely even there.
May I show you something?
Look over there.
The cyclate.
We spent much money creating a system
that keeps the water safe.
I even drank from it
to prove its safety.
It's a great photograph,
it's really a nice photograph.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome.
So...
Let's take a walk.
Do you know what we make here?
Toxic chemicals.
Good chemicals.
Chemicals that fertilize the land.
Help feed millions.
The chemicals needed to make plastics.
Even medicines.
Also chemicals for developing photographs.
And chemicals that make 35mm film.
Like the kind you use yourself, Mr. Smith.
We employ over 60 percent
of the residents here.
If the protesters succeed
and they put Chisso out of business,
what happens then?
I mean how the fuck would I know?
I know that you're broke, Mr. Smith.
That you owe money.
And that you are
on the brink of getting evicted.
You are correct, sir.
You are very correct.
But I've still got my youth.
And my girly charm,
which I think
will get me through.
A father is supposed to provide
and protect his children.
Obviously you care more about yourself
than your own flesh and blood.
Now you may choose to believe...
the small amount of the local fishermen
who claim that they have
somehow been harmed
by our methods.
But I am sorry to say
they are the parts per million.
Relative to the greater amount,
the greater good.
You know, for a second there I thought
you and I was gonna be good pals.
But I can see now
that I was sadly mistaken, because you,
sir are full of fucking shit.
- Please follow me.
- Certainly.
Why not?
Spanky and Alpha-alpha
gonna shoot me in the back?
I am a business man.
I make deals.
Like we have done with the locals
who have taken our payments
since the twenties.
It is even a line item in our budget.
Fifty thousand American dollars.
Here's the chance to amend your sins.
And...
Provide for the people
that counted on you.
You've had quite a career, Mr. Smith.
What else do you need to prove?
Chisso is winning back
the support of the people...
because we're influencing
student activists...
who are acting violently
against Chisso personnel.
This is not who we are.
Chisso are the ones acting violently.
We need to stay together on this
or we'll lose.
You know we'll lose!
We've offered good terms.
Chisso are promising
compensation will be quick.
We don't want
any more fighting in the town...
or shame brought to Minamata.
Chisso is behind this.
You are blind to it.
That's not true!
Is your goal to have Chisso
move somewhere else?
That's what they'll do
and where will our town be then?
This is not just about this town.
It's about big companies all over the world
invading the towns of
good, hard-working people,
and polluting their existence.
It's happened before...
and it will happen again!
Don't get so emotional!
Calm down!
Don't cause any trouble.
We understand how you feel.
We are all in the same pain.
But we all want it to end.
The signatures speak for themselves.
The people have spoken!
This is the right way
to settle the matter...
for all.
No more fighting!
May we see the book?
That's not necessary.
Have you pressed your signature
on this document?
No.
And you?
They have overwhelming
signatures of support in the book...
yet they won't show it.
Do we believe this is fair?
Let us see the book!
Show us! Show us!
That's my signature. I never pressed it!
That guy is dead. How could he have signed?
You're right. He is dead!
What's going on here?
Tell us!
You're full of lies!
Hello.
- Welcome.
- Sorry for the intrusion.
- Shoes.
- Oh, Goddamnit!
Excuse us.
Hello.
Thank you.
Let's eat together.
Good, right?
Can she see?
- No.
Akiko can't see or talk.
She's congenital.
The fetus has absorbed the mercury
sparing the mother.
Mr. Eugene, are you married?
He has two children.
Does he have photos of them?
What?
She's asking if you have
any pictures of your children.
Of my children?
You know, uh, no.
I'm ashamed to say that I don't.
It's bad.
Unfortunately,
he hasn't got any photos of them.
I need to help
Mrs. Matsumura at the market.
Okay.
Can you watch her?
- What?
- Akiko.
No.
No, I can't do that.
You'll be fine, we'll be back in one hour.
I am not the most responsible...
- Stop it.
- No.
Let's go.
I'll go out for a while.
Don't get worried.
I'll give you a bath soon, Akiko.
I'm not so good at these
kind of thing, you know.
Sorry.
Do you want to touch my beard?
There is not many beards out here, right?
Fuzzy? Fuzzy woozy?
♪ May God bless and keep you always,
let your wishes all come true ♪
♪ May you always do for others,
and that others do for you ♪
♪ May you build a ladder to the stars ♪
♪ And climb on every round ♪
♪ May you stay forever young ♪
♪ Forever young ♪
You're a good girl.
That way, we can't interfere.
You got company.
- You are Yamazaki Mitsuo, right?
- We will search the place.
What?
- Get the children inside.
- Don't get in our way.
Go. Go.
Don't take photos!
Don't resist!
You should be ashamed of yourselves.
Papa!
They're gone.
Everything is okay.
Mama!
Papa!
All I ask for are any negatives.
Any photos you've taken
while you've been here.
And that you go home immediately.
And let what is happening here
play out here among Japanese
in Minamata.
In a community and courts
where it belongs.
And where you don't.
On a scale of one to ten,
fuck you!
GENE IS AT WORK
- Yeah.
- Are you gonna eat?
Read the sign, Aileen.
I am being nourished by my own hunger.
And maybe just a tiny amount of whisky.
And maybe just a tiny amount
of amphetamine.
That's our little secret.
♪ Somewhere ♪
♪ Beyond the sea ♪
♪ Somewhere waiting for me ♪
♪ My love stands on the golden sand ♪
♪ And watches the ships ♪
Stop.
Jesus!
- Come.
- Bring water.
No, Gene, no, no!
Gene! No! Gene!
No more of this! No! No!
That's it. No, I'm done. No.
Don't you dare follow me.
I will ruin your fucking life.
No more. I'm done.
- Yes.
- You have a collect call from Japan
by a Eugene Smith,
will you accept the charges?
Can you ask him
to call me back in a few hours?
He is quite insistent that...
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
I'll accept the charges.
Hello Bob, Bob? It's terrible here.
Uh, listen, no fucking chance.
-  Gene, talk to me.
- Okay, I'm coming home.
Now we're not gonna get the pictures.
I mean I can't do this shit anymore...
By the way, it's been made
very clear to me now.
That I'm seriously unwelcome here.
Bob? Bob? What's wrong?
I went to the goddamn nat for you
and you ask me what's wrong?
Well, I hear, I'm sorry.
I don't give a fuck what you are.
Listen to me, I need the
pictures, Gene. I need this story.
And I need you
to get me this story
- like nobody else can.
- No, you don't.
Big people hurt little people.
Little people get hurt by big people.
Same thing here, same thing there.
This picture, that picture.
They all burnt up in the fucking fire.
Why does it matter?
And memory is the goddamn devil.
But the people over there, they matter,
right? I know that because you told me.
No, do you know what matters?
- Money, money for my kids.
- Have you been drinking?
Of course not, Bob.
I'm a professional, Jesus!
Gene, hang up, go back to sleep.
In the morning it'll all seem different.
You listen to me, pal.
I was recently quite reluctantly escorted
by a couple of goons
to go and meet the top fella
at the Chisso joint.
What the fuck are you talking about?
He offered me
a whole lot of money, Bob.
A whole lot of dough.
And I gotta say, I gotta say...
The dough was awful pretty.
- And you told him how long and hard to go?
- Yes, I did.
Yes, I did, like a dick.
And you know what,
I should've taken it.
But I'm a dick, I'm a dick, Bob.
Just like you're a dick.
And you know what?
Here's what I'm gonna do.
I'll gonna go right back there
and I'm gonna grab it.
- I'm taking it.
- Don't you dare!
Oh yeah, no listen...
I'll wire it to you, you take back
the six grand that I owe you,
and then you send this to my kids, OK?
Not okay, Eugene, not fucking okay!
You know how you always told me
how much your kids hated you?
You think a couple of grand
is gonna make a difference?
You really think your kids are that naive?
Oh, fuck you! I don't need
to listen to that shit.
You call me a sellout,
here is the irony,
I did, I did sell out to the board, to the
boys with the abacus in the basement.
- And now I'm gambling the reputation...
- Bob, are you gonna give me a pep talk?
Because I actually might need
to vomit first.
...67 percent ads and I'm losing.
Likely I won't even have my integrity
to fall back on in my old age.
But I will have yours!
Damn it, Gene! I will have yours.
I'll tell you what,
if there's any left,
I will stuff it into a fucking box
and ship it to you.
I don't know how many more issues I'm
gonna be able to publish, but one of them
is going to have the most important
photographic essay of the last 30 years
or I will personally fly out there
and kick your pathetic whinging ass.
The kids in the office, the special ones,
- they don't look up to me.
- Hey, Bob...
They look up to you.
Because you matter.
And in reference to your last comment,
blah, blah, blah...
Just bring me the story, okay?
Bring the story home.
Still there, Bob?
What the fuck? What's this?
- Shigeru.
You know there's a zoom
on that thing, right?
Zoom.
Do you have a gun or an aspirin?
Or any drugs? No?
You wanna take a picture?
Come here.
Some people may come and go
with the best of intentions...
but we can't count on them.
This is our fight.
Why do you think Chisso are hitting us...
harder and harder?
Why do you think they're getting
bolder and bolder?
You know why.
They can threaten us...
but we are going
to the shareholders meeting...
Excuse me.
Excuse me, I just want...
Would you...
Would you mind translating this for me?
Hi.
I'm really no good at public speaking.
I'm not good at public speaking.
I suppose that I'm one of those "pictures
worth a thousand words" type of guy.
I believe that a picture
is worth a thousand words.
Anyway, that doesn't matter.
I'm here to help
if I can...
But I need you to help me.
I want to help you,
but I need your help too.
By allowing me...
to spend some precious time
with you and your family.
I want to spend some
precious time with your families.
So that I can help
to fight your fight.
If I did this,
I will be able to help you
to win your fight.
So... I mean...
The question is this...
Who is comfortable and willing
to share these...
these very precious intimate moments
and to be photographed by me
with the utmost care and respect?
Does anyone agree to be photographed?
Thank you.
Thank you. Arigato. Thank you.
What?
Are you drunk?
What? Is it good? Or is it not?
No one is ever drunk...
If they can lie down on the floor
without holding on.
We're gonna do this together.
March 7th, 1971
You are murderers!
How many people are outside?
Over 500.
500?
Yes.
Get out of here.
I'm staying by you.
It's too dangerous, get out.
Gene!
Mr. President.
We know there is verdict
that will arrive soon.
We hope that Chisso will accept
responsibility for its negligence.
We are not here for luxuries.
Just to know that we will be looked after
and able to die in peace.
If you are human,
listen to what we are saying.
I and Sadae Ogata.
I understand that you don't know who I am.
But you should.
Both of my daughters fell ill.
Both suffered more than I can imagine
anyone suffering, let alone a child.
My eldest daughter suffered
from convulsions for months.
So much pain that she couldn't cry.
She is dead now.
And my other daughter, Miyuki...
will never be able
to spend a day without care.
My husband and I cry often.
We weep because we fear
for what will happen...
when we are no longer able...
to take care of her.
Mr. President...
You've got nothing to say?
You are a human being too, right?
We are the same, and yet...
how can we be this different?
How can we?
I am sorry. I truly am.
What? No.
What happened to you...
What you have gone through...
brings sorrow in our hearts.
Please forgive us.
She said you treat her
with much dignity and respect.
Thank you for that.
She said you made her laugh.
What the fuck is that?
My child also has Minamata disease.
He is nine years old.
I work on the boats still...
when the fishermen allow me to...
but because of my symptoms...
they don't want me on their boats.
So, it's my wife that needs to work.
She works on the boats sometimes...
and many nights she is forced
to take care of both of us.
She can't do that forever.
Can she?
Mr. President.
We know that you will pay
for the old victims...
but you must pay the same
for the new victims as well.
It's your responsibility!
Am I wrong?
Mr. Uyishi, can I have a moment?
Gene! Are you okay?
I'm OK. I'm OK. What's this?
Someone just brought it.
What the fuck is that?
What is that?
It came when you...
It's the negatives from our dark room.
I don't get this.
Where did it come from?
Thank you all for coming
and speaking with me.
Your plight brings me much sadness.
But we've added up
the costs of your demands...
- However...
- We simply cannot pay.
Unfortunately... this is our final answer.
I can't take this anymore!
Kyushi! Kyushi!
They don't believe we're in pain.
This blood is on your hands!
Kiyoshi!
Are you okay?
We are ready.
Can I move Akiko's legs?
Excuse me.
Can I move Akiko's left hand?
Yes.
Akiko, I will move your hand
Good.
Very good.
Beautiful.
- I can't.
- Wait.
Fuck it!
Do me a favor,
give me the... my shutter.
Thank you.
OK.
Son of a bitch.
He got it.
He fucking got it.
We have to pay.
Somehow we will find a way.
We must.
We won!
Today, we have won the battle.
But the war persists.
We must continue to fight.
To fight for our children...
so their children have something...
that they can fight for.
But all of you here...
and the people who stood with us...
have taught me that this a fight
we can win!
Go home tonight
and find some happiness with your families.
Because tomorrow we have more to do.
To fight for those that cannot.
Subtitled by CLARITY.
In the Spring of 1971,
Chisso Corporation agreed to fully reimburse
medical and living expenses
for the victims of Minamata disease -
the largest total sum ever
awarded by a Japanese court.
While this recognition
brought some relief,
neither Chisso Corporation
nor the Japanese government
has upheld the moral
and financial essence of this deal.
In 2013, the Japanese Prime Minister
declared
that Japan had recovered
from mercury pollution,
denying the existence
of the ten of thousands of victims
who continue to suffer today.
Life Magazine published
its last weekly issue on December 19, 1972.
"Tomoko in Her Bath" is considered
one of the most important images
in the history of photojournalism.
Gene and Aileen were married
on August 28, 1971, in Japan.
Gene died on October 15, 1978 -
indirectly as a result of the injuries
he received at the factory.
The Minamata photographs
were the last ones he ever took.
Aileen remains deeply engaged
with the Minamata community
and is steadfast in her fight against
environmental pollution to this day.